Boker tov. So today's daf is Tes-Vav, we will end the first
perek and begin the second perek today, and we start at the
very bottom of Yud-Dalet Amud Bet. And the issue is that the
mishna says you can send all various types of things on Yom
Tov according to Beis Hillel, as long as it's possible to use
on Yom Tov even if it's only theoretical. But one of the
things was kilayim shatnez. So the gemara wants to figure out what
can you use it for. And don't say you can use it
to sit on because then you're not wearing it, because rabbinically, although
that's biblically true, rabbinically we say you can't sit on it even
if it's at the bottom of ten cushions because of a concern
that you'll sit directly on it and the little string will go
on top of you and it'll be like wearing it. So the
gemara says ella, last word, last line on Yud-Dalet Amud Bet, ella
b'vilo. We're talking about a curtain. You can use it as a
curtain. You won't wear it, it won't touch your skin. Wonderful. So
there's not an issur hana'ah by shatnez, just of wearing. So gemara
says v'amar Ulla mipnei mah amru vilon tamei, but Ulla said why
did they say a vilon is tamei? Why don't they consider a
curtain part of the house for other halachos, for halachos of tumah?
Why is it considered a separate vessel? Mipnei she'hashamash mischamem kenegdo
because the attendant will warm himself, he'll stand by the curtain and
he'll wrap himself in it according to Rashi and he'll use it
to warm himself so it's not considered just a structural part of
the house. And if that's true in terms of qualifying it as
a vessel and being tamei, there should be a similar concern of
using it for shatnez because you'll come to wear it and warm
yourself with it and therefore you shouldn't allow yourself to have a
shatnez curtain either. So the gemara therefore says on Tes-Vav Amud Aleph,
still trying to figure this out, it says ella b'kashan. It must
be that we're talking about very stiff, hard type of a cloth
which is which there are no loose threads and which we'll see
in a minute won't produce any warmth and therefore there is no
concern that you will come therefore there won't even be a rabbinic
concern of that
sitting on it.
You're back to sitting on it, but it's hard, and that's a
good point because Tosafot discusses this and Rashi says it briefly, thank
you, and Tosafot discusses it at length, that to actually wear something
that's hard would not be allowed because that would be putting you
in the biblical category. But in terms of the rabbinic category, to
sit on it, which is the combination of sitting on it, which
is anyway biblically permitted, and it's hard, and therefore there's not a
concern that it'll come to, you know, a string will go on
you, if a string will go on you, it won't warm you,
and the idea of providing warmth is part of the definition of
wearing something that it provides warmth, then we will not we will
not rabbinically restrict it. Ki ha d'amar Rav Huna brei d'Rav Yehoshua
like Rav Huna the son of Rav Yehoshua said, hai namta gamda
d'Narash,
this like garment, this hard garment from the place of Narash, sharei,
you can it's permissible to now Rashi says not permissible to wear,
it's permissible to sit on, it's shatnez true, but it's hard and
you're sitting on it and therefore it's permissible. Amar Pappa says Rav
Pappa, ardelin ein bahem mishum kilayim. What are ardelin? So Rashi says
he has in if he found in the Geonic literature that it's
basically a type of a thing that you put at the heel
of your foot, or maybe not exactly clear from whether it's an
insole or it is underneath it or actually on the outside, you
know they buy these like rubber things that you that you tap
at the bottom so it doesn't ruin. But that would be even
more obvious, it sounds a little bit Rashi is a little bit
ambiguous but sounds like even as an insole that you put by
the heel of your foot, but again, it's hard and you're not
wearing it, although it's funny, like it's part of your clothing but
you're not wearing it, it's under your foot, and therefore it is
permissible.
Okay, so where is it? Ein bahem mishum kilayim because again it
is hard and something that's not on you but under you and
it's hard is not a problem. Amar Rava says Rava, hanei tzrari
d'pshiti, these little bundles of coins, you would like have a little
you know a money pouch, and the money pouch would be of
let's say it would be of shatnez. And what are you keeping
in the money, you're keeping coins. And then you keep the money
pouch like against your chest. So in that case ein bahem mishum
kilayim. There's no kilayim problem because again although again it's against your
body, it doesn't provide any warmth and this idea of providing warmth
is part of the definition of a clothing and of an issue
of shatnez.
Right so if I decide to use it as a belt, it's
certainly clothing but not providing any warmth and it's integral part of
my clothing that's that's the big problem.
Yeah so that's a good question and that goes back to the
point I said before that Rashi says all this issue about being
warm is when we're dealing with in the rabbinic area. When we're
dealing with biblical like biblical kilayim, something that you're actually wearing, really
wearing, not something you know that it's not. Now does that mean
then we would it would be rabbinically prohibited then you're right, then
maybe if you're really wearing it, it could be it's like a
biblical issue. How much is warmth you know an important it's a
very good question, how much is warmth an important characteristic of clothing
when something is in this sort of ambiguous zone. But if something
is real clothing it doesn't matter. Right, it's a very good question,
right Rashi is a little bit Rashi
says.
Okay now the גמרא Gemara says like this: so if it's if
you have coins in it, it's not a problem of course, even
though if it's against your chest and whatever because of just you
know the fact that the coins keep it stiff essentially it does
not provide warmth. However, the בזריני bazreini if you're keeping seeds in
it, so then it's much more malleable, right, the whole pouch, and
effectively it's not stiff anymore, יש בהם משום כלאים yesh bahem mishum
kilayim that is a problem. רב אשי אמר אחד זה ואחד זה
אין בהם משום כלאים Rav Ashi amar echad ze ve'echad ze ein
bahem mishum kilayim either way it's not a problem, לפי שאין דרך
חימום בכך. lefishe'ein derech chimum bekach. There's again the idea of warmth.
Although it provides warmth, that's not the normal way you warm yourself
with, so even though you keep it on your body, it's not
there to provide warmth. So very interesting the centrality of this issue
of defining something as clothing for providing warmth. But again, as Michael
asks as and as רש״י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot say, this is
a leniency within something that is not functioning normally as clothing. Something
functioning normally as clothing, we do not use this as an allowance.
Okay, now we go on. So that's you're allowed to send שעטנז
shatnez because again if it's hard שעטנז shatnez you can have some
use for it. אבל לא סנדל המסומר. Aval lo sandal hamesumar. You
cannot send a sandal that has nails in it, that does like,
apparently not the nails that are sticking out, although there was a
case with the nails sticking out. But anyway that has like the
that has, you know, nails around the edge. סנדל המסומר מאי טעמא
לא? Sandal hamesumar mai ta'ama lo? Why not? משום מעשה שהיה Mishum
ma'aseh shehayah because of the story. What story? So you should know
the story. So it's based off of—so when we learned how ever
long ago it was, מסכת שבת, Masechet Shabbat, we learned that there
was a story that there was the Jews were hiding from the
Romans in a cave and then they heard some sound and they
thought it was the Romans and they all started running out of
the cave and you know and like when they were—they were trying
to push each other out. I mean this happens nowadays like at
concerts right when these mobs try to leave soccer games, right? People
get trampled to death. So they were all running out of the
cave and they got trampled to death. And one of the reasons
that led to the people being hurt and killed was the fact
that they were wearing these sandals which not just had nails but
presumably the nails were coming out of the bottom and were like—they
were like cleats. Okay, but metal cleats. So there they said, okay
nobody can ever wear a סנדל המסומר sandal hamesumar again. So why
did you only say it on שבת Shabbat and יום טוב? Yom
Tov? So well that's when the story occurred. Realize like there's no
logic for דוקא davka שבת Shabbat and יום טוב. Yom Tov. I
would say another reason is it's like, you know, if you just
told somebody in general not to wear it, who's going to listen
to you? But if you say not to do something on שבת
Shabbat and יום טוב, Yom Tov, there's a million things you can't
do on שבת Shabbat and יום טוב, Yom Tov, so this is
part of the list. It's like they said like you know we're
about to come up to the ספירה Sefirah period, right? So רב
משה—so Rav Moshe somebody asked רב משה Rav Moshe like can you
listen to recorded music during the ספירה? Sefirah? So he said no.
So he said well like you know why not? I mean it's
only recorded. I mean what's the problem? He says look, I don't
think you can listen to recorded music the whole year but nobody
listens to music. All right, so here too at least we'll listen
if you tell us on שבת Shabbat and יום טוב Yom Tov
not to do it. So that's why—so therefore you don't send it
because it has no use. אמר אביי Amar Abaye said אביי, Abaye,
סנדל המסומר אסור לנעלו sandal hamesumar assur lina'alo you can't wear it,
ומותר לטלטלו umutar letaltelo but it's not מוקצה. muktzeh. If you can
find something to do with it, like scratch your back, that's okay.
אסור לנעלו משום מעשה שהיה assur lina'alo mishum ma'aseh shehayah you can't
wear it because of the story,
ומותר לטלטלו מדקתני אין משלחים umutar letaltelo midektani ein meshalchin because the
משנה Mishnah says you don't send it as a gift. אי סלקא
דעתך דאסור לטלטלו Ei salka daitach de'assur letaltelo if it was actually
מוקצה, muktzeh, השתא לטלטולי אסור בשלוחי מיבעיא hashta letaltulei assur bimeshalchin mibaye
if it's מוקצה muktzeh would you have to tell me you can't
send it as a gift? So it's not מוקצה, muktzeh, you can
have some use for it. It's just the רבנן Rabbanim said you're
not allowed to wear it. Now of course if that's all that's
true you're not allowed to wear it and you can have other
uses for it, why can't you send it? I'm sure the same
way you can find some use for an unsewn up garment and
for a piece of שעטנז shatnez you could find some use for
this type of a thing. But the—as is going to be clear
later, it's not—this is forbidden because not just because there's no use
for it but because if you send it as a gift somebody
will say oh you sent it to me as a gift that
means I can wear it and therefore you'll come to wear it.
So this they did not let you send as a gift. Okay
now ולא מנעל שאינו תפור velo min'al she'eino tafar not a shoe
that is not sewn, that the leather is not yet sewn against
the base.
פשיטא Pshita obvious there's no use for it. לא צריכא דאף על
גב דנקיט בפיסיכי. Lo tzericha de'af al gav denakite pasiche. Even though
it is—and רש״י Rashi has two explanations, but one is basically let
me just check רש״י Rashi here.
Where's רש״י? Rashi? Right, it's like it's the little pegs that are
keeping the leather attached to the base, but it's not really sewn
up. So therefore you might say oh temporarily I can wear it,
let's face it this really has no legitimate use. רבי יהודה אומר
אף לא מנעל לבן Rebbi Yehuda omer af lo min'al lavan even
not if it's white like the leather has not yet been blackened.
תניא Tanya taught in a ברייתא Baraisa רבי יהודה מתיר בשחור Rebbi
Yehuda matir bashachor it's okay once the leather has been blackened, ואסור
בלבן ve'ossur belavan but not when it's still white מפני שצריך ביצד
הגיר mipnei shetzarich betzad hagir because it requires like the blackening putty
to
you know rub into it. רבי יוסי אוסר בשחור מפני שצריך לצחצחו
Rebbi Yosi osser bashachor mipnei shetzarich letzachtzacho רבי יוסי Rebbi Yosi says
even if it's black it's still forbidden because it has to be
shined, it's not yet complete. So the גמרא Gemara says ולא כלי
velo kli it not they don't really debate. מר כי אתריה ומר
כי אתריה. mar ki atreih u-mar ki atreih. Each one goes according
to the way the shoes were in his place. באתריה דמר בישרא
לתחת b'atreih d'mar bisra l'tachat in the place of one of them
the flesh part was below meaning the skin, the leather that you're
using is it the part of the leather that was facing the
the flesh of the animal or part of the leather that was
facing the outside of the animal? So in and the difference is
that if it's the part that was facing the flesh, apparently it's
more cracked and it's more and there're just more crevices and therefore
it's not really a usable or it's not really a presentable until
you shine it. So in one place באתריה דמר בישרא לתחת b'atreih
d'mar bisra l'tachat the flesh part was the one that went against
your skin and therefore it did not require as much shining to
be usable because it was the skin part that was on the
outside. ובאתריה דמר בישרא דלעיל u-b'atreih d'mar bisra d'le'eil in the other
person's place the part of the leather that was the that was
adjacent to the skin of the animal was facing on the outside,
was facing above, and therefore it had more cracks and crevices and
it wasn't wearable until you would shine it.
You have to shine it for use.
Exactly. זה הכלל כל שנעשים בו ביום טוב. zeh ha-klal kol she-na'asim
bo b'Yom Tov. So the principle is anything that you could theoretically
use on יום טוב Yom Tov is something you can send as
a gift. Says the גמרא, Gemara, רב ששת שרא
להו לרבנן לשידורי תפילין ביומא טבא. Rav Sheshet shara lehu l'rabanan l'shidurei
tfillin b'yoma tava. רב ששת Rav Sheshet let the rabbis, the rabbinic
students, send תפילין tfillin on יום טוב. Yom Tov. Interesting, sounds like
לרבנן l'rabanan like the rabbis means rabbinic students but all of a
sudden there's this practice of doing it. Anyway now you're going to
obviously ask the question: what can you use תפילין tfillin for? So
אמר ליה אביי amar leih Abaye so אביי Abaye said to him,
והאנן תנן כל שנעשים בו ביום טוב משלחים אותו v'anan tnan kol
she-na'asim bo b'Yom Tov meshalechin oto anything that you can benefit from
on יום טוב Yom Tov you can משלחים אותו meshalechin oto you
can send it. So you can't use תפילין tfillin on יום טוב.
Yom Tov. So גמרא Gemara says no, הכי קאמר hachi ka'amar this
is how to read it: כל שנעשים בו בחול משלחים אותו ביום
טוב. kol she-na'asim bo b'chol meshalechin oto b'Yom Tov. The question is
what do the words ביום טוב b'Yom Tov modify? Is it כל
שנעשים בו ביום טוב משלחים אותו, kol she-na'asim bo b'Yom Tov meshalechin
oto, what's the language in the משנה? Mishna? It's זה הכלל כל
שנעשים בו ביום טוב משלחים אותו zeh ha-klal kol she-na'asim bo b'Yom
Tov meshalechin oto or כל שנעשים בו ביום טוב משלחים אותו? kol
she-na'asim bo b'Yom Tov meshalechin oto? Okay. Of course let's face it
that's a very hard read because of course we're talking about יום
טוב. Yom Tov. You don't need יום טוב Yom Tov to modify
משלחים אותו. meshalechin oto. Anyway that's how רב יוסף Rav Yosef is
reading it, that really even if you can't use it on יום
טוב Yom Tov even if it's only theoretically usable, רב ששת, Rav
Sheshet, theoretically usable on the weekday which of course then raises the
question of the סנדל המסומר. sandal hamesumar. So let's take a look.
So the רש"י ותוספות Rashi v'Tosafot discuss the סנדל המסומר sandal hamesumar
interestingly the גמרא Gemara does not and they basically say the problem
of the סנדל המסומר sandal hamesumar is not that you just can't
use it on יום טוב Yom Tov but that you send it
on יום טוב Yom Tov people will come to assume that they
can wear it. So and that's the problem whereas if you send
תפילין tfillin on יום טוב Yom Tov either a) everybody knows you're
not allowed to wear תפילין tfillin on יום טוב Yom Tov we're
not concerned about that or b) if you do wear it, this
is an interesting point, you don't transgress anything and this is a
fascinating idea we say תפילין ושבת לאו זמן תפילין. tfillin v'Shabbat lav
zman tfillin.
But let's say you do wear תפילין tfillin on שבת, Shabbat, have
I done anything wrong? Like what exactly have I
violated? So רש"י ותוספות Rashi v'Tosafot interestingly say you would do more
of a violation to transgress the rabbinic wearing of a סנדל המסומר
sandal hamesumar than to wear תפילין tfillin on שבת Shabbat and יום
טוב Yom Tov where it's לאו זמן תפילין lav zman tfillin but
you didn't actually violate anything by doing it which is a fascinating
idea. Okay so therefore yes in theory you could have sent the
סנדל המסומר sandal hamesumar were it not that we were afraid that
you would come to wear it.
Yeah the drill, things like מוקצה muktzah all this in the whole.
Right, so apparently you're right apparently according to this you could send
a כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור. kli shemilachto l'issur. So you could
find as long as it weren't that's the question. Is that considered
לצורך גופו לצורך מקומו l'tzorech gufo l'tzorech mekomo etc. but it's a
very good point it's very strange it's a broad expansion of what
the משנה Mishna allows. So let's take a look. And it does
raise other questions as we said because normally you're not allowed to
do a קנין kinyan on שבת Shabbat and יום טוב Yom Tov
except for the sake of for שבת Shabbat and יום טוב Yom
Tov itself. So here how could you even do a קנין kinyan
on it? But yeah it's quite fascinating. So let's see what the
גמרא Gemara says. גמרא Gemara moves on though. אמר אביי amar Abaye
so אביי Abaye says, אביי Abaye himself who asked the question maybe
he didn't like the answer so he said let's move
on. תפילין הואיל ואתו לידן נימא בהו מילתא. tfillin ho'il v'atu l'idan
neima behu milta. Since we're talking about תפילין tfillin let's talk about
something else. I don't really enjoy this conversation let's talk about something
else. So
היה בא בדרך ותפילין בראשו. haya ba baderech u-tfillin b'rosho. You were
coming in the way and you happened to be wearing תפילין tfillin
and שקעה עליו חמה shak'ah alav chamah and the sun set and
what's the big deal? So either it's a weekday and therefore it's
a problem about wearing תפילין tfillin at night or the way רש"י
Rashi says it it's Friday afternoon and now it's שבת Shabbat and
you're not supposed to wear תפילין tfillin on שבת. Shabbat. מניח ידו
עליהם עד שמגיע לביתו. mani'ach yado aleihem ad shemagi'a l'veito. You put
your hand over them you don't have to take them off because
if you take them off maybe you'll drop them if it's a
weekday. If it's שבת Shabbat you'll be carrying them. Obviously you can't
take them off so cover them so it's not obvious you're wearing
תפילין tfillin at night or on שבת, Shabbat, wait till you get
home.
Shouldn't you be embarrassed about a מצוה mitzvah though?
No, it's that you don't mislead people about the idea of wearing
שבת Shabbat at night or תפילין tfillin on שבת Shabbat or at
night. היה יושב בבית המדרש ותפילין בראשו. haya yoshev b'veit hamidrash u-tfillin
b'rosho. Now let's say you were in the study hall which is
out in the fields and it was you were wearing תפילין. Tefillin.
ושקעה עליו חמה. Veshaka Alav Chamah. I'm sorry, it skipped a line.
וקידש עליו היום. Ukiddesh Alav Hayom. See the difference between ושקעה עליו
חמה Veshaka Alav Chamah and וקידש עליו היום. Ukiddesh Alav Hayom. So
it says it's the second case we're talking about שבת. Shabbos. And
now became שבת, Shabbos, so in addition to the problem of wearing
תפילין Tefillin at night, it's wearing תפילין Tefillin on שבת, Shabbos, and
the prohibition of care, and you can't carry it, and you still
have to get it home. You don't want to leave it out
in the field or the בית מדרש. Beis Medrash. So מניח ידו
עליהם עד שמגיע לביתו. Maniach Yado Aleihem Ad Shemagia Lebeiso. Same idea,
you cover it, so you're wearing it. So although it's, you know,
it's not true that something that you wear necessarily means you're not
carrying. Like if you wear a key around your neck, you know,
like they have those key belts and whatever, so it has to
actually function as a garment. The fact that it's being worn as
opposed to being carried, wearing is a way of carrying. It has
to actually be a garment to not be a problem of carrying,
although you could argue that תפילין Tefillin is a garment, right, it's—but
anyway, but the point is that it's certainly not the דרך Derech
to carry something by wearing it, so at least it puts it
in the most things, so at least it puts it in the
rabbinic category. So they let you continue to wear it, and even
though you're carrying it, because it's not a normal thing that's worn
at night, they allowed you to not worry about that rabbinic thing
in order to get it to a place of safety, and even
though of course—what? Why in the בית מדרש? Beis Medrash? Because it's
out in the middle field, nobody's—the doors aren't locked, nobody's here to
protect it. Okay, so that's what you do. You're allowed to wear
it home even though it's שבת Shabbos not זמן תפילין, Zman Tefillin,
and even though, you know, it's actually a form of rabbinic carrying
because it's not a normal thing to be wearing now, they let
you do it to get it to a place of safety. So
the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay,
so גמרא Gemara says like this. Where are we? מתיב רב הונא
בריה דרב איקא. Maseiv Rav Huna Brei DeRav Ika. But so now
we have a ברייתא Braisa that says the same scenario but has
a different position about it. היה בא בדרך ותפילין בראשו וקידש עליו
היום מניח ידו עליהם עד שמגיע לבית הסמוך לחומה.
Hayah
Ba
Baderech Vetefillin Berosho Vekiddesh Alav Hayom Maniach Yado Aleihem Ad Shemagia Leavais
Hasamuch Lechomah. You can do the same thing, but you get to
the house that's closest to the wall of the city, meaning you're
going to bring it into the city environs, but you can't get
it all the way to your house. היושב בבית המדרש וקידש עליו
היום מניח ידו עליהם עד שמגיע לבית הסמוך לבית המדרש. Hayoshev Beveis
Hamedrash Vekiddesh Alav Hayom Maniach Yado Aleihem Ad Shemagia Leavais Hasamuch Leveis
Hamedrash. Or if you're in the study hall, you get it to
the first house, like a private house that they'll keep watch over
it, but not again that you're able to bring it all the
way home. So what's the story in these scenarios? Can you bring
it all the way home or did you have to drop it
off at the first house? So the גמרא Gemara says לא קשיא,
Lo Kashya, it's not difficult. הא דמינטרא הא דלא דמינטרא. Ha Demintara
Ha Delo Mintara. So
if it'll be protected in the first house that you get to,
then you leave it there. If it won't be protected, you bring
it all the way home. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute,
אי דלא דמינטרא, Ei Delo Mintara, if it's not in a state
where it would be protected, so מה ידו בראשו? Ma Yado Berosho?
Why are we only allowing it if you were already wearing it?
אפילו מונחין בארץ
נמי. Afilu Munachin Baaretz Nami. Even if the תפילין Tefillin were lying
on the ground, if they're in the state of not being protected,
we let you put them on and wear it as a way
of getting it to your house on שבת. Shabbos. דתנן, Detnan, we
taught in the משנה Mishnah in שבת, Shabbos, המוצא Hamotzei, תפילין—not—רש״י points
out it's not המוציא, Hamotzi, it's המוצא, you find תפילין—מכניסן זוג זוג.
You can bring them in one pair at a time, you put
them on and you wear them and you get them into the
house. So if we're talking that the problem here is that the
תפילין Tefillin are really in a place of not being protected, why
would we give the scenario you're already wearing them? We allow you
to put them on on שבת Shabbos and not be concerned about
wearing תפילין Tefillin on שבת Shabbos and not be concerned that it's
like a rabbinic form of carrying, we let you do it to
protect the תפילין. Tefillin So make up your mind. If it's not
protected, then even if you weren't wearing it, and if it is
protected and you're wearing it, why are you able to bring it
all the way to your house? So the גמרא Gemara says לא
קשיא, Lo Kashya, here's the difference. הא דמינטרא מחמת גנבי ומחמת
כלבי, Ha Demintara Mechamas Ganvei Umechamas Kalbei, or some of the גרסא—הא
דלא דמינטרא מחמת גנבי Ganvei, ומחמת כלבי. We'll read it that way,
it's a little more understandable. When is it that we allow you
to take it off of the ground and to wear it and
to get it home? That's if it's exposed to all types of
dangers: גנבי, Ganvei dogs, any type of thing. So then, lying on
the ground, you put it, you wear it, you bring it home.
You can—you wear it home. הא דמינטרא מחמת כלבי ולא דמינטרא מחמת
גנבי. Ha Demintara Mechamas Kalbei Velo Demintara Mechamas Ganvei. The case that
we're talking about that we only give you latitude if it actually
is—you're already wearing it, is when it is—when it's not exposed to
dogs, like it's in the בית מדרש, Beis Medrash, it's not exposed
to dogs, but the בית מדרש Beis Medrash isn't locked and גנבי
could still get into the בית מדרש. Beis Medrash. So in that
case, מהו דתימא רוב ליסטים ישראל נינהו ולא מזלזלו
בהו? Mahu Deseima Rov Listim Yisrael Ninhu Velo Mezalzelu Behu? Maybe I
would say, look, you gotta love this line, most robbers are Jews.
I assume it means most robbers in that area or something, I
don't know, it's such a bizarre line. Anyway, therefore, if somebody's going
to get into the בית מדרש, Beis Medrash, he's probably Jewish, and
a good פרום Frum גנב Gannav won't steal the תפילין. Tefillin. So
I don't have to—or even if he steals the תפילין, Tefillin. he
won't mistreat them, right? So okay, I'll lose my תפילין, Tefillin, but
the תפילין Tefillin, in terms of the קדושה Kedushah of the תפילין
Tefillin will be respected. He'll still treat the תפילין Tefillin properly. So
maybe I don't have any latitude, maybe I have to leave it
here
because it's not really protecting the קדושה Kedushah of the תפילין. Tefillin
קא משמע לן Ka Mashma Lan that no, you're allowed to continue
wearing it, but to actually put it on if it was שבת
Shabbos and they were in a place
that
you're only— But if you're already wearing it in that scenario we'll
let you to continue to wear it. So there's three cases. There's
three cases, I'm going to tell you there's three cases. One case
is where it's just exposed and if you don't do something the
dogs'll get to it and whatever, then you could wear it, put
it on, wear it and get it to the house. Second case
is is that yeah no picture whatever, yeah, your house. The second
case is is that it's only a concern of גנבים ganavim Jewish
גנבים ganavim which won't mistreat it, in that case you can't actually
put it on if you're not already wearing it but if you're
already wearing it you can wear it and you can bring it,
you could bring it home, you could bring it to the first
you could bring it all the way home. And then the third
case you're already wearing it but it's you're not really afraid about
it being exposed to any type of a danger and then we
let you bring it only to the first house. Okay, הדרן עלך
פירקא, Hadran alach pirka, that was the end of that of the
first פירקא. pirka. Yes.
I'm sorry what?
No, no, you don't. Okay. So now I'm not talking about this
anymore. We have limited time. I'm not talking about it, we're starting
the next פירקא. pirka. Okay. So so now we move on from
that פירקא pirka which had a lot of מוקצה, muktzah, but interestingly
got into as you saw a lot not only a lot of
other דרבננס d’rabbanans about יום טוב Yom Tov but some very important
questions about which דאורייתא d’oraisa מלאכות melachos can be done on יום
טוב. Yom Tov. And now we turn to this פירקא, pirka, which
starts us on really quite new topics, and a very interesting one
and again בית שמאי, Beis Shammai, there's so much of of מסכת
ביצה Masechet Beitzah that's all debates of בית שמאי בית הלל. Beis
Shammai Beis Hillel.
Let's take a look. יום טוב שחל להיות ערב שבת. Yom Tov
she’chal l’hiyos erev Shabbos. Okay, יום טוב Yom Tov falls out on
ערב שבת. erev Shabbos. So this is a one-day יום טוב, Yom
Tov, like you're talking about ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, so it's a
Friday. לא יבשל בתחילה מיום טוב לשבת. Lo yevashel betchila miyom tov
l'shabbos. You cannot at the outset, like just סתם, stam, cook
on Friday יום טוב Yom Tov for the sake of שבת. Shabbos.
אבל מבשל הוא ליום טוב ואם הותיר הותיר לשבת. Aval mevashel hu
l'yom tov ve'im hosir hosir l'shabbos.
But you can cook for יום טוב Yom Tov and leftover food
that you cooked on יום טוב Yom Tov you can use on
שבת. Shabbos. Now you might think that the idea of this משנה
mishna is like with a wink and a nod. Cook a lot
for יום טוב Yom Tov wink wink and if there's leftover use
it for שבת, Shabbos, but the גמרא Gemara is actually going to
say no, you cannot do it דרך הערמה. derech haarama. You cannot
do it as a trick. It's only if if you very genuinely
were trying to prepare for יום טוב Yom Tov then you can
benefit but you can't pretend that you need a lot in order
to be leftover. So if you really want to be cooking for
שבת, Shabbos, the idea is not to hope that there will be
leftovers, but to do a עירוב תבשילין, Eruv Tavshilin, which is the
next line. ועושה תבשיל מערב יום טוב, Veoseh tavshil meerav yom tov,
here's what you really can do. You can cook a dish on
ערב יום טוב erev Yom Tov וסומך עליו לשבת vesomech alav l'shabbos
and rely on it for שבת Shabbos to continue cooking on יום
טוב Yom Tov for the sake of שבת. Shabbos. Since the idea
is what you cooked ערב יום טוב erev Yom Tov was for
the sake of שבת, Shabbos, the עירוב תבשילין Eruv Tavshilin is for
the sake of שבת. Shabbos. It's considered like you began your שבת
Shabbos preparations on Thursday ערב יום טוב erev Yom Tov and therefore
you can finish them up on יום טוב Yom Tov and that's
how עירוב תבשילין Eruv Tavshilin works because it's not בתחילה. betchila. It's
not you're just starting to cook on יום טוב Yom Tov for
שבת, Shabbos, you already started on ערב יום טוב. erev Yom Tov.
Now why is that? What's the logic? We'll see in the גמרא.
Gemara. But let's first before we get to the logic let's see
the debate of בית הלל בית שמאי. Beis Hillel Beis Shammai.
בית שמאי אומרים שני תבשילין ובית הלל אומרים תבשיל אחד. Beis Shammai
omrim sheni tavshilin u’Beis Hillel omrim tavshil echad. Now how much do
you have to cook? בית שמאי Beis Shammai says two separate cooked
dishes and בית הלל Beis Hillel says one cooked dish. How we
get to our מצה matzah and
our egg, we'll talk about.
Can it be like two types of rice? Or does it have
to be... Well let's take a we'll see we'll get to the
גמרא. Gemara. ושוין Veshovin and they agree בדג וביצה שעליו bedag uveitzah
she’alav if you have like a fish and batter, שהן שני תבשילין.
she’hein sheni tavshilin. בית שמאי Beis Shammai would concede that I'll consider
the fish one and the egg with the batter two. So בית
שמאי Beis Shammai is a little flexible in how to consider the
second one. Okay. מה? Mah?
Tempura. I'm sorry? Tempura. Tempura. Oh right, yes. Oh I thought you
were saying some Hebrew word I didn't understand. אכלו או שאבד Achlo
o she’avad if you ate the עירוב תבשילין Eruv Tavshilin or it
got lost, even though you made it ערב יום טוב erev Yom
Tov once it no longer exists לא יבשל עליו בתחילה. lo yevashel
alav betchila. Then right now it's now יום טוב Yom Tov and
you're trying and you want to cook. Oh I made it ערב
יום טוב. erev Yom Tov. Doesn't matter. In order to continue cooking
now for שבת, Shabbos, the עירוב Eruv still has to be around.
ואם שייר ממנו כל שהוא סומך עליו לשבת Ve'im shayar mimeno kol
shehu somech alav l'shabbos but if even a little bit of the
עירוב Eruv is still left over then you can continue cooking on
יום טוב Yom Tov for the sake of שבת. Shabbos. So there's
an interesting thing of two or one, but the more interesting thing
is why is it that just because you started on ערב יום
טוב erev Yom Tov can you continue cooking on יום טוב Yom
Tov for שבת. Shabbos. So let's take a look. מנא הני מילי?
Mena hanei milei? Where does this come from? אמר שמואל דאמר קרא,
Amar Shmuel d'amar kra, the verse says. Now everybody says we're not
really learning it from a verse the whole thing is רבנן, rabbinic,
but let's take a look. It's an אסמכתא. asmachta. זכור את יום
השבת לקדשו. Zachor et yom haShabbos l’kadsho. Remember שבת Shabbos keep it
holy. זכרהו מאחר שבא להשכיחו. Zochreihu me’acher sheba l’hashkicho.
Remember it because you'll come to forget it. Now what does it
mean you'll come to forget it? So the רש"י Rashi and ר"ן
Ran have an interesting debate what this means. רש"י Rashi means you'll
come to forget it because we're so focused on the שמחת יום
טוב simchas Yom Tov and all the cooking that we're doing on
יום טוב Yom Tov and that you're allowed to cook on יום
טוב Yom Tov and that you're allowed to cook on... that we're
just going to not bother preparing much for שבת Shabbos and we're
just going to do all of our cooking for יום טוב Yom
Tov and that's why we'll come to forget it. So you make
something on ערב יום טוב erev Yom Tov to remind you comes
יום טוב Yom Tov that you still have some that the שבת
Shabbos is still coming up. When you made ערב יום טוב erev
Yom Tov for the sake of שבת Shabbos you remember oh yeah
there's still שבת Shabbos coming we still have to prepare for שבת.
Shabbos. So you're just going to forget about it because you're so
involved in יום טוב. Yom Tov. The ר״ן Ran says no, the
reason you're going to forget about it is because of the prohibition
of יום טוב. Yom Tov. Since you're not allowed to cook from
יום טוב Yom Tov for שבת, Shabbos, you'll forget about שבת Shabbos
in the practical sense, not like you'll forget about it, but you'll
come not to have prepared for it because you'll be restricted in
what you're allowed to do on יום טוב. Yom Tov. So there
has to be a way where talk just just wait. There has
to be a way that we are going to give you some
latitude. So again for רש״י Rashi the point is you make the
עירוב eruv so you don't forget about שבת Shabbos and this is
actually going to reflect the two opinions we're going to see in
the גמרא Gemara of how the עירוב eruv functions. רש״י Rashi just
says you get caught up in יום טוב Yom Tov and forget
about שבת Shabbos and the ר״ן Ran says you'll forget about it
because you won't be able to cook for שבת Shabbos because of
the prohibitions of יום טוב. Yom Tov. So we need some solution
to remember שבת Shabbos and to give us the allowance to cook
for שבת Shabbos and that solution is עירוב תבשילין. eruv tavshilin. Now
מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, now the גמרא Gemara gets to okay how
does that translate into what the
how the עירוב eruv actually functions. אמר רבא כדי שיברו מנה יפה
לשבת ומנה יפה ליום טוב. amar Rava kedei sheyivru maneh yafeh l'Shabbos
u'maneh yafeh l'Yom Tov. So that's sort of like reflecting how רש״י
Rashi explained the idea forgetting יום טוב. Yom Tov. You'll really forget
to prepare for שבת. Shabbos. So therefore if you set something aside
on ערב יום טוב erev Yom Tov then you will remember come
יום טוב Yom Tov that oh yes I have to make sure
that I set aside and I have a nice meal for שבת
Shabbos as well. Doing of the עירוב תבשילין eruv tavshilin ערב יום
טוב erev Yom Tov reminds you when it comes יום טוב Yom
Tov to prepare for שבת. Shabbos. Now what you are saying to
yourself is okay what does that have to do with allowing me
to cook? It's reminding me to prepare. And the way the ר״ן
Ran even asks the question further is he says look what's going
to happen. The purpose of demanding that I make an עירוב תבשילין
eruv tavshilin is to remember come יום טוב Yom Tov that I
prepare for שבת. Shabbos. Let's say I forgot to make an עירוב
תבשילין, eruv tavshilin, right? So I forgot to have שבת Shabbos in
mind on ערב יום טוב. erev Yom Tov. Then comes יום טוב,
Yom Tov, what's the consequence? I can't prepare for שבת. Shabbos. So
it actually makes it even worse. Point was to ensure I cook
that I would have something for שבת. Shabbos. So says yes but
the as the way the ר״ן Ran says it is better that
this יום טוב Yom Tov you should be penalized and not be
able to prepare for שבת Shabbos so that next יום טוב Yom
Tov you make sure that if you want to prepare for שבת
Shabbos you're keeping it in mind from the outset. So basically it
works the opposite. It's not like we need something to allow you
to cook on יום טוב. Yom Tov. Really in principle the way
this would be phrased you're allowed to cook from יום טוב Yom
Tov to שבת. Shabbos. But we're afraid you'll be sloppy you won't
do what's necessary you'll forget about שבת. Shabbos. So in order to
ensure you keep שבת Shabbos in mind we're going to forbid you
to cook from יום טוב Yom Tov to שבת Shabbos unless you've
done something ערב יום טוב erev Yom Tov to remind you about
the importance of שבת Shabbos and
to begin the preparations of שבת.
Shabbos. Exactly exactly do it so you take care of it beforehand.
So the whole idea here is not like we normally think. It's
not as the way the way this the debate is framed by
the ראשונים Rishonim is is it לכבוד שבת l'k'vod Shabbos or is
it לכבוד יום טוב. l'k'vod Yom Tov. So the issue here is
or it's not that you need something to allow cooking from יום
טוב Yom Tov to שבת. Shabbos. No that's anyway allowed. But in
order to force you to remember שבת Shabbos on יום טוב Yom
Tov we're going to forbid you to cook on יום טוב Yom
Tov for שבת Shabbos unless you've done something ערב יום טוב erev
Yom Tov to remind you about שבת Shabbos and to begin the
preparations of שבת Shabbos one minute. That's the position of רבא. Rava.
Okay now רב אשי Rav Ashi אמר רב אשי amar Rav Ashi
says a much more logical thing. כדי שיאמרו אין אופין מיום טוב
לשבת קל וחומר מיום טוב לחול. kedei sheyomru ein ofin miYom Tov
l'Shabbos kal v'chomer miYom Tov l'chol. That no we want to do
this because if we don't do this people will think oh יום
טוב Yom Tov isn't important you can cook from יום טוב Yom
Tov to שבת Shabbos and then they'll start cooking from יום טוב
Yom Tov even to a weekday. So to underscore the importance of
יום טוב Yom Tov that it's not so easy to cook on
יום טוב Yom Tov to the next day we only will allow
you to cook on יום טוב Yom Tov to שבת Shabbos if
you're not really starting to cook on יום טוב Yom Tov for
שבת Shabbos you're just finishing up what you did yesterday. So according
to him and that's much more logical there's fundamentally a problem of
cooking from יום טוב Yom Tov to שבת Shabbos or if you
could do that certainly a problem of cooking יום טוב Yom Tov
to חול. chol. So it's not going to be easy to cook
from יום טוב Yom Tov to the next day from יום טוב
Yom Tov to שבת Shabbos and the only way we'll allow it
is in a framework that you're not really at the outset doing
it you're just wrapping up something you began earlier. So this is
framed that we do it לכבוד יום טוב l'k'vod Yom Tov as
opposed to doing it לכבוד שבת. l'k'vod Shabbos.
Yes this is my question. So you know what about הכנה דרבה?
hachanah d'rabbah? Doesn't he say it's דאורייתא? d'oraisa? But you're sort of
forgetting about that. Because here according according to the first part of
the line he's saying it really is okay but רבה Rabbah said
it's like
דאורייתא. d'oraisa. הכנה מיום שישי לחול מכאן hachanah m'yom shishi l'chol meichan
but יום טוב Yom Tov cannot be
מכאן meichan to שבת. Shabbos. But so what do you do about?
Yes so תוספות Tosfos a very good question so תוספות Tosfos discusses
it earlier and a little bit if I remember correctly a little
ironically תוספות Tosfos says that that has to do something that's all
it's lack it exists in the world and all it's missing is
preparation that's not Not in the category of הכנה דרבנן. hachanah d'rabbanan.
So it's real ironic because the whole פסוק pasuk is את אשר
תאפו אפו. et asher tofu efu.
So here, I'll read you תוספות. Tosfos. Good question. תוספות Tosfos on
ב עמוד ב. beis amud beis. וכי תימא על ידי עירוב תבשילין
v'chi teima al yedei eruv tavshilin just listen. וכי אתי תקנתא דרבנן
וליעקר הכנה דאורייתא? v'chi asi takanata d'rabbanan v'lyekar hachanah d'oreisa? By עירוב
תבשילין? eruv tavshilin? ונראה ליישב ד- רבא גופיה אזיל לטעמיה דאיכא הואיל
ומקלעי אורחין v'nira l'yashev d'Rava gufei azil l'taamei d'ika ho'il u'miklei orchin
oh that's another תירוץ. teretz. Okay
so there's other ways of dealing with it but you should be
very happy to know that תוספות Tosfos asks your question. It's a
very good question.
זה המנה יפה zeh hamaneh yafeh is it adding like your egg
and your matzah?
It's a reminder it's like a string around your finger that that
itself is the מנה יפה. maneh yafeh. It reminds you yes. Now
okay so that's the two explanations. One is they both say that
obviously biblically you have to be allowed to cook from יום טוב
Yom Tov to שבת Shabbos because some דרבנן d'rabbanan עירוב תבשילין eruv
tavshilin won't allow something that's biblically forbidden. Okay but according to the
first approach it's that we make it forbidden unless you take care
of this
and the purpose of taking care of this is a reminder to
make good food for שבת. Shabbos. And the other approach is no
it's fundamentally problematic although technically allowed to cook from יום טוב Yom
Tov to שבת Shabbos and to make it more permissible we have
to do it in the framework of finishing up the cooking that
you did for your עירוב תבשילין. eruv tavshilin. Okay so now the
גמרא Gemara says like this.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this תנן. tenan. Our משנה Mishnah
says עושה תבשיל מערב יום טוב וסומך עליו לשבת. oseh tavshil me'erev
Yom Tov v'somech alav l'Shabbos. You have to make it ערב יום
טוב. erev Yom Tov. בשלמא ל-רב אשי דאמר כדי שיאמרו אין אופין
מיום טוב לשבת היינו דמערב יום טוב אין ביום טוב לא. bishlama
l'Rav Ashi de'amar kedei she'yomeru ein ofin mi'Yom Tov l'Shabbos hainu de'me'erev
Yom Tov in b'Yom Tov lo. But yet according to רב אשי
Rav Ashi why you have to make the עירוב תבשילין eruv tavshilin
on ערב יום טוב? erev Yom Tov? Because the whole idea is
to emphasize that it's a cooking that has to begin beforehand. You
can't fundamentally designate יום טוב Yom Tov to cook for שבת. Shabbos.
You can just be wrapping up what you did on ערב יום
טוב. erev Yom Tov. אלא רבא מאי איריא מערב יום טוב? ela
Rava mai irya me'erev Yom Tov? According to רבא Rava why would
it have to do it on ערב יום טוב? erev Yom Tov?
אפילו ביום טוב נמי? afilu b'Yom Tov nami? Even if you made
an עירוב תבשילין eruv tavshilin on יום טוב Yom Tov you're doing
something to remind you it's יום טוב Yom Tov yes and I'm
going to remember that I have to prepare for שבת Shabbos that
I have to set aside food for שבת. Shabbos. So the גמרא
Gemara says אין הכי נמי in hachi nami in principle you're right.
Since it's only to remind you to set aside food for שבת
Shabbos you could make an עירוב תבשילין eruv tavshilin on יום טוב.
Yom Tov. אלא גזירה שמא יפשע. ela gezeirah shema yifsha. The only
reason not is that you'll be negligent. Once if you don't if
you're allowed to wait till יום טוב Yom Tov begins in order
to make it you'll forget about it and then comes יום טוב
Yom Tov and you'll forget about it as well. The whole problem
here is that you'll get caught up in יום טוב Yom Tov
and forget about preparing for שבת. Shabbos. So in order to force
you to remember it goes into your list of pre-יום טוב Yom
Tov preparations. Okay. So but some questions still persist.
Then you're still stuck. You're this no you're not allowed to. Right.
No we've never heard that anybody allowed an עירוב תבשילין eruv tavshilin
on יום טוב. Yom Tov. So there's a lot of things that
we force you to do you know with very counter-productive consequences but
that gets you in the right mindset. That has the larger
larger benefit. Okay. ותנא מייתי לה מהכא. v'tana meisei lah meihacha. And
the author of the ברייתא Baraisa uses the following verse as the
basis. את אשר תאפו אפו et asher tofu efu there you go
there's your הכנה דרבנן hachanah d'rabbanan ואת אשר תבשלו בשלו v'et asher
tevashelu bashelu
bake what you're going to bake cook what you're going to cook.
מכאן אמר רבי אליעזר אין אופין אלא על האפוי mikan amar Rabbi
Eliezer ein ofin ela al ha'afui you only continue baking on baked
things that you've begun baking before for on יום טוב Yom Tov
for שבת. Shabbos. ואין מבשלין אלא על המבושל v'ein mevashelin ela al
hamvushal and you continue cooking on יום טוב Yom Tov for שבת
Shabbos on things you began cooking before. מכאן סמכו חכמים לעירוב תבשילין
מן התורה mikan samchu chachamim l'eruv tavshilin min haTorah and here's where
they use the support the basis of the idea of עירוב תבשילין
eruv tavshilin but again a continuing of cooking seeming to be along
the lines of רב אשי. Rav Ashi. The fact that it mentions
bake and cooked is going to lead to our idea of a
matzah and an egg seeing baking and cooking as different things we'll
worry about that later. Let's end with the following nice little אגדתא.
Agadata. תנו רבנן tanu rabbanan our Rabbis taught because we just mentioned
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and here we're going to have a רבי
אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. מעשה ברבי אליעזר שהיה יושב ודורש כל היום כולו.
maaseh b'Rabbi Eliezer shehaya yoshev v'doresh kol hayom kulo. There's a story
that רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer was giving a דרשה drasha was giving
a שיעור shiur on יום טוב Yom Tov and it was going
on and on and on and on and on. He was giving
a שיעור shiur on יום טוב. Yom Tov. בהלכות יום טוב. b'hilchos
Yom Tov. It was the הלכות halachos of יום טוב. Yom Tov.
יצתה כת ראשונה. yatzta kas rishonah. The first group started looking at
their watches and they and they snuck out whatever at 10 AM.
אמר הללו בעלי פטסות. amar halalu baalei pitasos. So he said ah
those people are people with huge barrels of wine. They have to
go home because they have a lot of food that they're going
to eat. They're very indulgent. כת שניה kas sheniyah the second group
then then snuck off. אמר הללו בעלי חביות amar halalu baalei chaviyos
ah these are people with barrels not large barrels you know they
got big they they got big appetites they've got a lot of
food that they're running home to. כת שלישית kas shlishis the third
group. אמר הללו בעלי כדים amar halalu baalei kadim they're people of
like a pitchers okay so you know they have a meal not
a huge meal but they're still leaving they're still running after their
food. כת רביעית kas revyis the fourth group. אמר הללו בעלי לגינים
amar halalu baalei luginim which are I don't know some smaller types
of a of a of a you know of a vessel. כת
חמישית kas chamishis the fifth group. אמר הללו בעלי כוסות amar halalu
baalei kosos so cups they have cups of wine waiting for them.
התחילו כת ששית לצאת. hischilu kas shishis latzes. The sixth group. They're
already it's going on and on okay people are getting hungry. אמר
הללו בעלי מארה. amar halalu baalei me'eira. These are people of curse.
Now that's much more harsh than earlier. So רש"י Rashi says yeah
because he's afraid... nobody's going to be left in the בית המדרש
Beis Hamedrash now. The ערוך Aruch has an interesting interpretation. He says
they're cursed because like they lose out in both ways. They didn't
stay for the whole שיעור, shiur, but they're going home so late
they're not going to get a good meal, so they're like they're
losing out in both directions. Okay, נתנו עיניו בתלמידים, nosnu einov b'talmidim,
so then he started looking at his students like with presumably not
a nice look. היתה פניהם משתנים, hayesa p'neihem mishtannim, they start like,
you know, because the only people left in the בית המדרש, Beis
Hamedrash, like the ציבור tzibur was there, but the only people left
were the students. So they started like their face started changing colors,
they started thinking now he's going to be angry at us. אמר
להם, amar lahem, he said to them, בני, banai, my sons, לא
לכם אני אומר, lo lachem ani omer, I'm not angry at you
when I say מארה me'arah or whatever, אלא להללו, ella l'hallalu, these
people that are leaving, they're the ones I've got a problem with,
שיצאו, sheyatzu, שמניחים חיי עולם, shemanichim chayei olam, they're leaving the eternal
life תורה Torah ועוסקים בחיי שעה, v'oskim b'chayei sha'ah,
and they are and you know they're they're more focused on their
food than on the opportunity to learn תורה Torah on the רגל.
regel. בשעת פטירתן, beshas petirasun, it doesn't mean when they died, when
they left, and finally the שיעור shiur was finally over, אמר להם,
amar lahem, then he said to them, לכו אכלו משמנים ושתו ממתקים
ושלחו מנות לאין נכון לו, lechu ochlu mashmannim ush'su mamtakim v'shilchu manos
l'ein nachon lo, eat delicacies and drink sweet drinks and send gifts
to someone who has nothing prepared for him. כי קדוש היום לאדונינו,
ki kadosh hayom l'Adoneinu, today is sanctified for our God. That's by
in this story by עזרא Ezra talking. Anyway, so now it's time
to eat, now you can enjoy your food, okay, but so you
waited until the שיעור shiur was over.
Exactly,
exactly.
ואל תעצבו, v'al te'atzeivu, do not be distressed, כי חדוות השם היא
מעוזכם, ki chedvas Hashem hi mauzchem, the joy of God is your
strength, presumably תורה. Torah. Don't be, presumably
he's reading the verse, don't be distressed that you didn't get a
big meal because ultimately you're being supported by the joy of תורה.
Torah. But now you can go home and enjoy your יום טוב
Yom Tov meal. Okay, now that's quite fascinating, so that he doesn't
want people to be eating, he wants people to be staying in
the בית המדרש Beis Hamedrash all of יום טוב. Yom Tov. So
אמר מר, amar mar, let's look at this, שמניחים חיי עולם ועוסקים
בחיי שעה. shemanichim chayei olam v'oskim b'chayei sha'ah. והא שמחת יום טוב
מצוה היא, v'ha simchas Yom Tov mitzvah hi, what is he giving
people a hard time that they're going home to eat, שמחת יום
טוב simchas Yom Tov is a מצוה. mitzvah. רבי אליעזר לטעמיה, Rabbi
Eliezer l'taimei, he goes according to his reasoning, דאמר שמחת יום טוב
רשות, d'amar simchas Yom Tov reshus, that whether to translate שמחה simcha
in the context of physical pleasure and is a, you know, is
a רשות, reshus, is optional. דתניא, detanya, we taught in the ברייתא,
braisa, רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, אין לו לאדם ביום טוב
אלא, ein lo l'adam b'Yom Tov ella, what you should do on
יום טוב, Yom Tov, make a choice, אלא או אוכל ושותה, ella
o ochel v'shoseh, spend the whole day eating and drinking, או יושב
ושונה, o yoshev v'shoneh, or sit and learn. It's all or nothing.
Okay, there's two ways of having שמחה, simcha, תורה Torah and food,
and make your choice. So the people that left early presumably his
only problem was was that if you were wanted to be eating
you should have stayed at home in the first place. Spend the
whole time at home or come to the שיעור shiur and stay
in the שיעור, shiur, but don't come to the שיעור shiur and
then leave in the middle.
That's a great point by the way, רבי אליעזר
לטעמיה,
Rabbi
Eliezer
l'taimei, I was wondering about that too. רבי יהושע אומר, Rabbi Yehoshua
omer, there's the famous debate and רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua says חלקהו,
chelkeihu, no, he's more reasonable, people are not all one or all
the other, some people want a little תורה Torah but also want
to enjoy a nice
meal. חציו להשם וחציו לכם, chetzyo l'Hashem v'chetzyo lachem, you can have
שמחה simcha both in the spiritual sense and in the physical sense.
אמר רבי יוחנן, amar Rabbi Yochanan, ושניהם מקרא אחד דרשו, ushnihem mikra
echad darshu, they both learn from one verse. כתוב אחד אומר, kasuv
echad omer, עצרת להשם אלוהיך, atzeres l'Hashem Elokecha, it's a holy convocation
to God. וכתוב אחד אומר, v'chasuv echad omer, עצרת תהיה לכם, atzeres
tihyeh lachem, it's for you. הא כיצד, ha keitzad, how do you
reconcile, is it for you, dedicated to you or dedicated to God?
הא כיצד, ha keitzad, רבי אליעזר סבר, Rabbi Eliezer savar, או כולו
להשם או כולו לכם, o kulo l'Hashem o kulo lachem, either all
to God or all to you. רבי יהושע סבר, Rabbi Yehoshua savar,
חלקהו חציו להשם וחציו לכם, chelkeihu chetzyo l'Hashem v'chetzyo lachem, half and
half. By the way, it's quite fascinating because you'll remember from סוכות
Sukkos that it was רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that said that, you
know, משבח אני את העצלנים, meshabei'ach ani es ha'atzlanim, that don't leave
their houses on the רגל regel and they're מקיים, m'kayem, you know,
ושמחת אתה וביתך. v'samachta atah u'veisecha. So you shouldn't be going and
visiting your רבי rebbe in the רגל, regel, you should be staying
at home and being with your wife. And here he's saying stay
at home but spend all the time in the בית מדרש, Beis
Hamedrash, so I'm not exactly clear about that because there he really
emphasizes the the you know more לכם lachem aspect of it. Okay,
so now we're going to see besides that that was a fascinating
just discussion about יום טוב Yom Tov and שמחת יום טוב, simchas
Yom Tov, a tie-in to עירוב תבשילין. eiruv tavshilin. So the גמרא
Gemara says מאי לאין נכון לו, mai l'ein nachon lo, what does
it mean give, send, send gifts to one who has nothing prepared
for him? אמר רב חסדא, amar Rav Chisda, למי שלא הניח עירוב
תבשילין. l'mi shelo hinniach eiruv tavshilin. Ah, somebody who didn't make an
עירוב תבשילין. eiruv tavshilin. So he's not going to have any food
on שבת Shabbos because he can't cook on יום טוב Yom Tov
for שבת, Shabbos, so him you have to give your gift, you
know, send portions of food to him. איכא דאמרי, ika d'amri, some
say
מאי לאין נכון לו, mai l'ein nachon lo, it meant somebody who
didn't have a chance to put down an עירוב תבשילין, eiruv tavshilin,
he was very busy right before שבת, Shabbos, him we can have
רחמנות rachmanus on and give him some of our food. אבל מי
שהיה לו להניח עירוב תבשילין, aval mi shehaya lo l'hinniach eiruv tavshilin,
somebody who had an opportunity ולא הניח v'lo hinniach and didn't, פושע
הוא, poshea hu, he's negligent and maybe we don't have, we shouldn't
have רחמנות rachmanus on him, we shouldn't even send him food on
יום טוב, Yom Tov, which is quite fascinating. We'll get to that
whole idea of relying on an עירוב eiruv that the רב rav
made, etc. One last
line, מאי כי חדוות השם היא מעוזכם, mai ki chedvas Hashem hi
mauzchem, the joy of God is your strength. אמר רבי יוחנן משום
רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Amar Rabbi Yochanan mishum Rabbi Elazar berabbi Shimon
אמר להם הקדוש ברוך הוא לישראל amar lahem hakadosh baruch hu leyisrael
God says to the Jewish people בני banai my children לוו עלי
lovu alai borrow against me עלי וקדשו קדושת היום alai vekadeshu kedushas
hayom and devote the money to
make it a
sanctified day to have a beautiful יום טוב Yom Tov buy food
even if you have to borrow money האמינו בי eminu bi have
trust in me God is מעוזכם mauzchem your strength ואני פורע va'ani
poreia and I will and I will manage to I will pay
up for you I will pay your debts. Okay and now so
again the idea of how much we have to invest for שמחת
יום טוב. simchas yom tov. We will continue with this tomorrow.